hi welcome back to ayandagana and we're
now we're still in the middle of chapter
which is an examination of fire and
firewood
and this was supposed to clear it up
uh you know whether the seer
is there before the seeing
and especially before the thing you see
or is the seer come later or do they
come at the same time
and is it even possible
that we are seeing things the way we
think we are
uh if you are
not seeing things
the way you think you're seeing things
then sooner or later you get in trouble
you start fighting with your husband or
you do things
that don't make sense to make things
happen okay like i don't know in your
business
you take actions
which don't result in the result you
think they do
because you don't understand this
question
uh is the seer seeing something before
this the thing is there or is the thing
there first and then the person sees it
later
and of course it applies to medicine
buddha you know if you're doing a mantra
what's the time frame between you and
the mantra do you come first and then
you do the mantra
but how can you come first if you're a
mantra
practitioner because you haven't done a
mantra yet so actually the mantra should
come first and then the person who says
it should come later but then a mantra
can't say itself
and it gets confusing and if it gets
confusing to you
you are on the right track and if it's
not confusing
you're on the wrong track okay uh if it
seems confusing to you
then it's shaking up your normal way of
seeing things which according to
buddhism is always wrong you have always
been wrong your opinion
about whether the mantra came first or
the mantra came first or how the mantra
works if you think you know
you're probably making a mistake
and then when you say the mantras they
are not as effective it's not as
powerful it's much more powerful
if you understand how it really works
and it's like the relationship between
wood and fire firewood and fire
so we're halfway through our examination
of firewood and fire
and here we go we're going to go to
verse number eight
and it says
is it the case that we have a fire which
is depending on the firewood
or
kyoto is it the case that we have wood
which depends on its identity fire wood
which depends on its identity for fire
so the fire would have to come first
because it can't be firewood if it came
first before the fire you have to have a
fire
and then you say oh this wood is
firewood
okay but if you don't have the wood
first
before it's firewood how can you have a
fire and how can you have a fire from
wood which is not firewood
okay something's fishy something's wrong
okay
uh kang de mein nashin gerwa
and somebody says you know
i think they kind of depend on each
other you know the the fire needs the
wood
to start burning
but the wood needs to fire
before you can call it firewood okay so
somebody says why occasionally i think
it's kind of like they're depending on
each other you know uh okay
but then we have to still uh have a
question of which came first the chicken
heart egg which came first the firework
of the fire okay tango drupal it means
which one came first okay
why
why is that important now listen and
think about it
because the second thing to come
always depends on the first thing to
come okay the second thing that comes
always depends on the first thing that
comes
curing cancer with the mantra comes
second
and that depends on the mantra coming
first right
but if it's that the mantra depends on
the curing
in other words
if it doesn't cure cancer
then it's not really magical words is it
it's not really a mantra
so in that case
first you should cure somebody with some
kind of words
and then those words will become a
mantra
but then how do you know what words to
say
if you don't know if they're a mantra
yet you could just read the side of a
cereal box or something
and see if it helps you know so it
doesn't get to be a monster until you
kill somebody
but then if if it doesn't get to be a
month until you cure somebody
you'd have to keep saying different
words until something worked and then
then that would be a mantra see what i
mean
so
don't forget that the the second thing
to come
has to depend on the first thing to come
okay is it that
the cancer is cured
rests on the manta
or is it that it's the mantra rests on
the cure because the mantra is not
special words until there's something
happens from it okay
okay
you know
if it's the fire that came first
uh and then that depends on the wood
madhupala dubai thin fire could have
happened with no wood if the fire
comes first
and then the wood becomes firewood
well then the fire doesn't depend on the
wood because the thing it depends on
comes has to come first right
uh if if the fire comes first
and then it depends on the wood
then in the very beginning of the fire
there could be fire with no wind okay
before it before it was depending on the
world okay
if the wood came first
maybe by the way we're on yeah verse
nine men made by young
then uh
without a fire the wood would be
firewood okay before there was any fire
uh there would be would be firewood
before you saw a fire
come from it you could call it firewood
okay
all right and we have a picture here of
firewood okay
and uh
the idea is i mean
it's not firewood yet until there's a
fire okay it looks you know it looks
like somebody tied it up
it looks like somebody cut it in a
certain way
we don't know for sure yet though that
is firewood we don't know if someone's
not using these sticks for something
else okay
so until there's a fire
this is not firewood
and until there's firewood there's no
fire
and so
maybe things don't happen the way we
thought okay maybe the mantra doesn't
fix the cancer maybe something else
is creating the mantra and the cancer
and the fix of the cancer okay
like maybe our seeds maybe our mental
seeds and then well how do you
use that gesture how do you apply that
to your life
well then it makes sense to save animals
lives
because then the mantra will work
against the cancer for example there
would be seeds
in your mind for a cause-and-effect
relationship between
the mantra and the curing the cancer and
and
you know i did a three-year retreat uh
2000 to 2006.
and
i remember we had a lady in the retreat
she wasn't from our lineage she was from
a different village but she begged me
you know could i set up a cabin could i
could i do this for you retreat we had i
don't know five six people
in different cabins yours and she said
can i can i do it with you guys and we
said okay
and she got permission from her teacher
and
and then i remember um
before the retreat and after retreat we
couldn't talk during the retreat but um
we used to have very uh
we used to have very uh intense
discussions
and she would say and it was a very uh
interesting question she would say
the power of your teacher does not come
from you
okay everything else maybe comes from
you everything else comes from your
seats but the power of your teacher
is just in your teacher you know that's
that's that doesn't come from you you
know
whether you're a good person or a bad
person
it doesn't matter what seeds you have
doesn't matter
if a person is your teacher
then then there's power the power the
person has power and then we'd say well
yeah but buddha said it the first lines
of this book
say uh buddha said everything comes from
khans and everything comes from seeds
that's the first lines of the guardian's
most famous book
you know kang kashi tanjin
those are the
first words everything comes from seeds
so
so it's not that a mantra has power
it's not that a mantra has power even if
it has been spoken by a buddha
if you don't have the seeds for it to
have power
it doesn't have power okay and or else
the buddha was wrong
or else or else the person you say has
the power didn't have the power
okay
okay got it
if the power if the buddha has power in
and of himself or herself
then everything they say is true if the
buddhist sin
all things come from seeds
then even the power of the buddha
comes from seeds okay got it
and it can't be wrong because the buddha
that you say doesn't come from seeds
said
it okay all right
okay all right here we go that's very
negative right all right okay uh
next verse
if the fire depends on the firewood
then the fire
if if the wood came first and the fire
came second then uh turjan cayenne de
dugna
if the thing being depended upon by the
fire which is the firewood okay
doom
what did the firewood depend on to be
called fire firewood okay
so okay i understand that dependence
goes one way if i say is there a
dependent origination
is there a dependent relationship with
fire
then you say yeah well what well the
fire depends on the firewood you know
you can't have a fire without some fuel
okay yeah but on the other hand
the wood depends on the fire okay that's
what it says here jirjah means the wood
that the fire is depending upon
cayenne they do not as soon as you have
the firewood
well what did it depend on to be called
firewood okay that's a question
[Music]
i like to call it a ladder with no wall
okay and here's a picture of it
it took me a while i was trying to make
a ladder with no wall it's almost
impossible
but
anyway it didn't come out that great
but try to imagine a ladder
that's leaning on nothing okay and then
that's what
it would be
if the fire was firewood before the fire
started
then you could have a ladder you could
get up on a ladder
that wasn't leaning on a wall okay and
and that leaning on the wall
is is dependence and that's dependent
origination and we're going to talk a
lot about
the words for dependence and what
dependence means
does the curing cancer depend on the
mantra
or does the mantra depend on carrying
the cancer
or do they both depend on something else
okay and that's what we would say
and that's what nagarjuna is
there's a reason why we we took our body
to the valve
from
whose ceremony
regards
we took our vows
which is the permission we need to study
medicine buddha
we have to take valve and the most
famous ceremony is nagarjuna so maybe
nagarjuna knows something about medicine
but okay
all right uh
here we go
uh verse 11.
there's a very important word here
called
and uh
this is interesting for us it means
things happen
because of other things okay
and the most famous uh i think uh
sugan's text the mixed nuts text
we are translating a very difficult
commentary by vasa bundu
on the wheel of life
and you will see there
the definition
of dependent origination the definition
of dependence practitioner
is
okay turned up here's the word to do
to do means everything
everything that changes
happens based on something else okay
everything that changes in the universe
happens depending on something else the
two may not be
and the very very earliest statement of
it is by lord buddha and he said if this
happens
that will happen
and if that happens
this must happen
okay and he's like this you can see him
you know
uh
if this happens
then this will happen
it's like your mom used to tell you
right if you do this
this is gonna happen you know and if
this happens it's because you did this
okay
then i don't know after that it got
complicated people started calling it
dependent origination
in the beginning it was very simple you
know if this if you do this guys you're
gonna get this okay that's to do okay
okay
how could fire depend on wood
and now now we get into a tricky thing
with nagarjuna okay
and it seems a little
unfair
okay
if you back him into a corner
if you say yeah but you can't have a
fire without a firework you know
and he said well okay okay
but the fire you think you're getting
th the fire you think you can't get
without firewood it doesn't exist anyway
and you're like wait wait wait now
you're changing uh yeah now you're
changing things you know he says yeah
well
don't tell me the fire depends on the
wood because the fire can't exist anyway
you know well what do you mean the fire
you're thinking of can't exist why
because you think it comes from wood but
i'm trying to improve it comes from it i
know but that means you think it comes
with but it yeah i think you have some
wind that's what i'm trying to prove to
you but the fire you think comes from
wood can't come from wind so you can't
prove the fire comes from ruin because
the fire you want to prove comes from
wood doesn't exist
and it's like you're frustrated you're
like
man i was trying to prove something to
you it's like having a discussion with
your wife okay
[Music]
okay
then
the other guy is funny
means well what the hell you know the
guy said i don't care you know
means
it's a very short word right
but it means
anyway
okay the guy is
anyway the fire does depend on the wind
okay they need to minimal
and then the guy says no
you can't have
a ladder
leaning on a wall that's not there
okay you can't have a ladder
leaning or depending on a wall
if the wall's not there okay what's not
there there's no firewood there why
there's
there's no fire yet how could it be fire
maybe it's i don't know what they're
gonna use to build a cafe when they get
a permit in three years
okay something like that
you don't know what the word is yeah
okay
all right
and then uh i like this picture this is
an old picture that we use in dci it's a
pen
parts of a pen on the table okay
uh i hope so
and uh
the point the point here is that the
resting of the pen on the desk is also
not self-existent okay
uh
we we went through many times
why it's not a pen
until the seed opens in your mind we
talked about that countless times okay
but now if you look at the pen
resting on the table the pen resting on
the desk that's also coming from your
seats the dependence
of the pen on the part sitting on the
desk is also coming from your seat
okay all right next verse
now some guy says uh
i have a i have an option one
uh
the fire depends on the wood and it
doesn't depend on the wood at the same
time how's that
you know he's like getting frustrated
and saying the fire doesn't depend on
the wound
because it's not firewood yet and the
firewood needs to fire before he says
look okay regardless i have a suggestion
let's do both at the same time okay the
fire uh
depends on the wood
and it doesn't depend on the wind at the
same time how's that
then you're happy and i'm happy okay
there's no fire that could depend on the
wood
and there's no fire that couldn't depend
on the wind therefore
and there's no wood that could depend on
the fire
and there's no wood that couldn't depend
on the fire okay there's no fire that
doesn't depend on wind
but there's no fire that does depend on
wood
there's no wood that depends on the fire
to be firewood and there's no wood that
doesn't depend on the fire to be fired
how's that let's leave it like that
you know the other guys
you can have your cake and eat it too
and the gardener's uh
answer is ridiculous okay and
i try to make a ridiculous picture okay
patchy really i don't know
i hope it's ridiculous
it's a cup on the table
i don't know
i i tried really hard on this one
the cup's
on the table but it's not on the table
because the table's on the cup okay
at the same time the cup is on the table
and the table's on the cup so you
negotiate you don't have to struggle
deciding whether the fire
rests on the wood or the wood rest on
the fire how about both
let's do both unfortunately the cup
would only be one right
and and then it'd be difficult
to make a photo of it okay almost
impossible i think so
all right
let's go to the next verse uh he splits
the next verse into two
okay and when he does that there's
always an important reason for that so
we're gonna take half of ours
which is 13 a okay
and it's very simple mainly
your man yeah and what this means is the
other guy says
uh
you could see it okay if you can see it
if
if you can see fire
burns wood
then fire
does have a nature and it burns things
okay don't tell me nothing has its own
nature
you don't have to be a philosopher
to see that things are not empty
they are something they're not empty
fire is not empty why
you can see it burns wood okay if it
fire burns something
then you can't say it has no nature it
has a nature what's its nature it burns
things duh you can see
stop hassling me you know that's how
okay the other guy is like open your
eyes in the car look i probably he lit a
match or something
he said look the fire's burning okay got
it
don't tell me it doesn't have a nature
of its own don't say the match fire is
empty
because it's not empty because it's
doing something if you can see
that it's doing something it's not empty
okay don't give me this empty stuff okay
so that's a very very uh
the in tibetan
the other guy says look if a fire burns
a piece of wood
then when some get on it if you can see
it with your own eyeballs
then the fire has its own nature then
it's not empty of any nature of its own
okay now uh
now we're going to get to mcgarjon's
answer but first of all
he says
and there's an american english
expression seeing is believing seeing is
believing the other guy says look seeing
is believing and the guardian says let
me show you a picture now
let me show you a picture with somebody
with certain glasses on
okay
and there's an expression in american
english called
looking at things with the rose-colored
glasses and and actually i gave a talk
once uh
long ago and i bought a hundred pairs of
these glasses
and i handed them out to everybody
and i said is the world pink and they're
all like yes
you know and i yeah i can see
it's pink so it must be you said if you
can see something is a certain way
it must be that way you know and a guy
says yeah okay well put on these glasses
is everything pink yeah is it really
that way uh
okay
no yes it is because you're seeing it
seeing is believing okay if you see
everything in the universe is pink then
it must be pink that was your argument
okay then the guy says no no you've you
messed up my eyes you put these pink
sunglasses on me yeah well maybe without
the sunglasses your eyes are messed up
okay all right maybe you're messing up
everything all the time anyway
and that's the idea okay so
you know the wheel of life teaching
is basically that your equipment is
messed up
okay your eyes are already tinted
and you can say you know fire must
depend on wood because any fool can see
it
yeah but if the way you look at things
you're always a fool
okay all right okay
uh okay here we go to the next half
verse i guess
okay tension
uh
he goes an interesting strategy and by
the way this whole book
and most of nagarjuna's books are like a
military campaign i saw a movie about
alexander the green
he's so cool i mean he was a brutal
killer but
his first great battle i think he's got
40 000 macedonians
against a million persians
and he's 21.
and
and you know it's 21.
and he goes out there and he's like
okay i got an idea and he
his strategy is so cool
he rides out with a hundred guys and
they take off that way
so that the soldiers are facing the
soldiers right he comes out with like
100 guys and he runs that way with his
horses you know
and uh the other generals like where's
he gone there it is i don't know you
know we're supposed to go like this and
fire this one you know
what what's he doing he's gone somewhere
but you you you kidding you follow him
you know find out where he's going and
then he circled around the general was
no longer
protected the persian general and
i just got it
now why are we talking about that
the guardian does the same thing he sees
this whole thing as a almost like a
military company okay
and here's his next his next move okay
here's this next move
daesh and shingen hagman
mean means
leftover right tim sagama means leftover
he says look let's just stop there about
the fire in the fire it's been going on
too long it's already two classes
you know let's let's just finish it okay
it says anything else you wanted to say
about the firewood just stop okay and
the guy said whoa wait
he says go back to song the mason
go back to the
chapter about walking down a path which
is the second chapter okay coming and
going going and coming
he says look i don't have to do this
whole argument with you
i'm tired this chapter we got to go on
the next chapter you know it's already
too much time
uh let's get on to the next chapter you
you if you want to talk more about
anything else about firewood can you
just go back and read the second chapter
okay again
i told you everything
what did he tell us in the second
chapter anybody
remember something about there's three
parts to the path
three parts to a road
do you remember
there's the part you already
walked on
then there's the part you're gonna walk
on
and then there's the part you're walking
on now now how wide is the part you're
walking on now is the question
you know okay like your foot goes like
here's the path and your and your foot
heels touches first
and then your
then your toes take off right heel
foot
toe
this part
is the path you already went on
this part is the path you didn't go on
now exactly where is the line
between those two well it must be
halfway well let's wait till you put
your foot down
okay
and you want to call it uh halfway
halfway the foot yeah yeah okay well how
where's the halfway point on your foot
you can't find it okay you can't really
find it
any line you draw
if you can see the line
it already has width
so it already has a part that you went
on already and a part that you didn't go
on already
okay we'll split that one guess what
okay let's put that one
and then that has wig and that has part
that you went on and part that you
didn't go on and the answer is there's
no part that you're walking on now
you're always either
walked
on something or kind of walk on
something but you're never
walking on something so if you're not
walking on something how can you ever
have walked somewhere before and how can
you ever going to walk on something
because you're not walking
what it's all you know just
you're just splitting here you know yeah
but no it's important you think you're
walking but you're not maybe the path is
moving
okay
maybe your mental pictures are getting
bigger bigger bigger bigger big as you
go through a door right
bigger bigger bigger door smaller
smaller smaller door and you call it
walk into a door but maybe you're not
walking through a door maybe your mind
is making small door big door picture
maybe you're standing in the same place
all the time
okay something like that
girl what's the point of all that
well then it means you're creating the
door and you're creating the passage to
the door and that means you can go
anywhere you want
if it's coming from here
then you could walk planets you could
you could act out your china okay that's
how you're gonna
be a buddha you know oh if you say
medicine buddha mantra you become
medicine buddha yeah what's that all
about well then you can go to different
planets and help people at the same time
why because the planet get bigger bigger
bigger when you arrive and planet gets
smaller smaller smaller when you go to
the next planet
that's all coming from your mind hey why
not just do it all at the same time and
then you're everywhere and you can help
everybody at the same time okay that's
all
if the travel to other planets was
coming from anywhere else except your
suits it's impossible
you can't there's the why there's no
place you are now
okay got it it's very sexy because of
emptiness you can become medicine
and if you don't understand that you
will never become a medicine boy okay
got it
okay so he says go back to what i told
you before now
grandpa likes to take you back to the
i could just go on to the next verse but
why didn't i take you back
to the last verse okay we don't have it
on the
thing um
anyway i went back and got the whole
second chapter is all about that walking
thing okay
and the guy's you can feel like he's
almost impatient now he wants to get on
to his 11th chapter
right and he said like just
remember what i told you about the
walking thing okay
by the way every text i saw or many of
the texts they misspelled the walking
thing
and it spell it if you spell it wrong it
becomes meditation
and then it gets messy uh so it's useful
to have the sunscreen okay
all right
which means i don't know i was in a mood
the picture the next picture we're going
to look at
to me the most important application of
fire
is making a pizza
in a fire brick oven do we have any
around here though
yeah oh
uh
yeah so if you can't decide you know is
the fire burning the pizza or is the
pizza causing the fire to be caused the
fire called the fire because it gets
cooked by the thing
you know
and i think
the discussion of whether the pizza
defines the fire or the fire cooks the
pizza
right
what's it similar to
what where did what did nagarjuna just
say
what did he just say you can't find
yeah you can't find the now therefore
you cannot bake a pizza
that's why they're parallel that's why
he wants to bring the second chapter
into the tenth chapter you can't find a
place
where the pizza is cooking
okay
in time temporarily you cannot find a
place where the pizza is done
okay it doesn't exist
you know and he's just sitting in front
of the guy and he's like i'm so tired of
this fire and and uggni
you know the guy says well what do you
have any last words you want to give me
you know you can't have a pizza why
there's no moment when it's done okay
got it
because the pizza doesn't depend on the
fire and the fire it's not a pizza fire
until the pizza is done
got it all right all right
i don't know why i decided to use a
pizza
hey g
let's buy a pizza on the way home okay
okay
i'll tell you the english of the old
verse okay uh whichever that part i've
already translated so
first of all having gone is not going
neither is not having gone going and yet
except for having gone and not having
gone you can never be stepping
okay that's the that's the that's part
of the lines that he's talking about
okay
uh
all right
oh and then there's another verse later
on that's relevant and he says
fire as an example to establish seeing
is not something which can having gone
or not gone
or stepping down
offers a reply to the one who is tied to
seeing
in other words if you believe your if
you always believe your eyes
then i'll give you the argument about
walking okay you cannot you cannot
always believe your eyes why i i told
you about the walking thing
okay it looks like there's a place where
you're walking but there's not
so don't trust your eyes right that's a
that's the subject we're on right now
don't trust don't tell me
the fire must depend on the wood because
you can see it burns when there's wood
there
okay and then we say don't trust your
eye okay you also think you're walking
don't you
you also think you're walking through a
door but you never are
but my eyes tell me so yeah that's the
problem
okay all right
and
we can go to verse 14. this is a long
one i'm sorry
i think nagarjuna also like wants to get
on to the
next uh
nagarjuna here uh he gives four he he's
kind of making a review and he says
let's look at the four possibilities
here shinny manimante shingles
uh
here's the four possibilities so
regardless kind of summarizing
look what is not fire
wood is not the fire why
and and by the way i want you to think
about this
because the way tony llama does it it's
a little bit tricky okay you ready
wood is not the fire
because in that case the agent would be
the action
that makes what the agent
okay
so it's not that fire is burning wood
it's that wood is feeding a fire
okay who came first
is
is the fire burning the wood is that
what this chapter is all about
and and charlie llama says oh no no
the wood is feeding the fire
the fire is the object of the action
not the agent the wood is feeding the
fire okay then the guy says well i
thought the fire was burning the wood
i thought the fire was the asian and the
wood was stopped
then nagarjuna says well think about it
you know you also thought you were
walking
i'll say it again okay by the way i'm
sorry we have to go so fast we're trying
to get through this book in five years
you know and this is the only way we are
right now today we are moving at five
we are moving at one wisdom for five
years
okay and if we move slower it's gonna be
20 years or so really
okay here we go
[Music]
and you're meant to look at these videos
again and again and again until you get
it okay
all right
uh what is not the fire
because then the agent would be the
action okay
and that when you say it that way who's
the agent
i'll say it again what is not the fire
because if the wood was the fire the
agent
would be the action
he's saying the fire is the object of
the
wood
the wood is feeding the fire that kind
of implies the wood came
right first and then it's feeding the
fire okay and he says i want you to say
the fire is burning the wood
then the
fire came first and the wood came second
right
sorry
but yeah the fire came first in the wood
cancer
all right uh
so are they the same thing
is the fire the wood no
i mean either the fire is burning the
wood or the wood is feeding the fire
okay
but they can't really be happening at
the same time okay
then the second one is uh
is the wood separate from the fire
and he says no it's not
why because when you say separate from
the fire you think they never overlap
you know when you say rebecca is
separate from michael
then what you mean is they're not
siamese twins somewhere
you know she's over there i'm over here
okay so it must be some
line between them okay that means they
don't overlap
they can't overlap well okay if they
never overlap
then they can't have a relationship okay
not possible if the fire
never touches the wood
there can't be burning okay but if it
does touch the wood then there's a place
where the wood is the fire
no no no the woods over there the fires
over there
and they touch yeah but where did they
touch
uh they touch where they they this is
this spot where they touch each other so
they have to overlap in a tiny space
there okay if they don't then there's
always a line between them then the one
can't burn the other because it never
touches the other if it does touch the
other there must be some kind of overlap
there okay
okay if the wood is not separate from
the fire
uh
you couldn't have the the fire burning
the wood because the fire is the one
okay
all right uh
that's the fire involved the wood
no
uh
is the fire completely
devoid of wood
no because then it wouldn't burn okay so
these are the four choices i'll say them
again
and again you don't have to understand
it the first time just keep listening to
it
if you think you understood the guardian
of the first time you read it
you must be drawn crystal monkey all
right
uh
wood is not the fire because then the
agent of the action would be the action
okay
uh wood is not separate from the fire
because if they were separate then there
couldn't be a fire
uh fire doesn't involve wood because if
it did
some part of the fire would be the wood
and if you say that's ridiculous then i
say well
okay
then water can cause fire why because
they don't touch
if fire were devoid of wood there would
be no fire
if fire had no relationship that would
how could you have a fire okay
what's really happening when fire burns
wood
you have the karma to have a fire that's
all you have the seeds to have a fire
the wood is not causing the fire the
wood is not
feeding the fire and the fire is not
burning the wood your seeds are opening
that's all that's all that's what
nagarjuna wants either that's all he
wants he did
to understand the fires not burning the
wood and the wood's not feeding the fire
your seeds are opening
and you see a fire okay and forget stop
thinking
that the wood causes the fire or stop
thinking that the fire is burning the
wood stop thinking like that my seeds
are opening into wood my seeds are
opening into fire okay that's all start
trying to think like that my seeds are
opening into medicine buddha mantra and
then my seeds are opening into the
cancer is stopping my and my seeds put
them together
okay my seeds make them cause it affects
they are not cause of effect
they can't be causing effect because one
can't touch the other okay
no more than
where you went and where you're gonna go
can never touch
okay
all right
[Music]
let's go to the next verse i'm sorry
this this one's really low
made on pushy
this is a pretty profound
verse he says look we spent all these
two classes
talking about wood and fire okay
nearer lamborghini i want you to apply
that to all actions
by all people
okay
for example
to what we had in the previous chapters
seeing hearing smelling tasting
feeling there's an agent which is your
eyeball there's a blue color out there
the eye the agent acts towards the
object
okay
try when you're struggling with
understanding how you can see something
when you're struggling with
understanding how a mantra works please
just go back to the fire in the wood
that's what he's saying
he says use it for everything
then he says
kailash
coffee cup
and
nambu means
a bolt of cloth
and he's just taking two things in the
room okay the eyeglasses and the coffee
okay the eyeglasses in the car okay what
i said
about the fire
and the firewood what i said about the
eye
eyeball and the blue color hey look it's
like the same with everything
okay eyeglasses coffee cups
vases
bolts of cloth it's the same with
everything okay
malabari
you can explain every goddamn thing in
the world if you just get this fire and
fire with things straight okay
what the fire is not feeding the side
the fire is not burning forward and the
fire is not treating the fire okay if
you can get it okay then you understand
everything
all right apply it to everything i have
a picture here
i was trying to think of two things in
the world
you know two things in the i don't know
there should be a refrigerator and a car
but maybe i messed it up oh there we go
yeah you can apply it to everything
refrigerators cars
you know
uh bolts of
cloth in the old days they didn't have
cars and refrigerators so he had to say
both o'clock and water water vase is a
popular example because there was no
plumbing
in any of the houses you had to have of
this so
it's a good example because it's always
there
okay you always have one
okay if you've ever lived in a village
in india you
the kailash the water
the water vase or pot is a very
important thing in your life that's all
your water for the day
you walk a mile to the well you get it
you put it on your head you bring it
home
and that's what you wash from that's
what you cook from okay that's what you
yeah
okay i have we've got another verse here
i don't know what happened
condom
oh this is the final verse i think and
it's very funny oh no it's yeah is it
yeah it's the final verse very cute
he says
the fire and the wood are the same thing
or
if you think the fire and the wood are
separate
question
i don't think you're so smart
okay so means
right okay by writing
like stage
yeah
if thou thinkest
that the fire is the wood or if thou
thinkest
that the fire and the wood are separate
i don't think it's
that thou is too smart
and that's his last word and he's kind
of insulting
last word okay
means if you think you're a smart guy me
sam
i don't think so
okay if you don't get the firefighter
thing
then you're a fool okay that's all all
right
and if you're full then you're always
gonna be suffering okay uh
somehow you're always gonna be suffering
[Music]
okay now i thought uh since we have a
few minutes
where what oh man my computer just
freaked out
yeah
oh yeah
uh
you got a picture for me
gutty i keep wanting to call you city
just clean your name
yeah
i heard tim likes turtles so i got a
turtle picture
okay i love this picture this is an
ancient belief in india
that the whole universe is held up by a
turtle
okay that the universe exists on the
back of the turtle okay
now listen
if you're wrong about the turtle that
holds up the world
you're wrong about everything in the
world
got it
if if you think the world is being held
up on eternal by
what's being held
held up on the turtle's bed the world
how much stuff is in the world
everything in the world
okay then you're wrong about every
goddamn thing in the world okay got it
okay if you think the world
exists on the back of eternal
then how many things are you wrong about
everything on the back
how much is that
that's everything
so
uh
you know by the way people are always
bringing me books all the time you don't
know
and i don't know why they especially
when i leave
a city or a country they always give me
some book at the airport
and uh
it's like oh guess what i read this it's
just like what you teach
you know i'm like i don't think so
but i i'm always polite i take the book
you know and i have a a game i play with
myself while i'm waiting at the passport
line
i i open the book at one sentence and i
look at it
and if it's not ridiculous i might read
the another page
but if the one sentence is ridiculous
then when i get to customs and i make
sure that people aren't looking at me
anymore and then i throw it out
i throw the book out and then my friends
are like gishlar why don't you give it
to the
to the charity store when you get home
no i don't want to because it's totally
wrong
i don't want to be responsible for
someone else getting a stupid idea in
their mind that's gonna cause them
suffering for the rest of their life no
the only thing you can do with this book
is toss it you know
and uh
and hope that the garbage guys aren't
really
uh i'm not being sectarian i'm just
saying
if negation is is correct so far
then everything we know
everything that was taught to me at
princeton university was wrong
everything it was all on the back of the
turtle
okay the basic premise was wrong
everything about it was wrong one thing
can cause another that's wrong
okay then all science all philosophy all
music all our everything is wrong
okay all right got it everything if you
think that world's on the back of a
turtle
then everything you think about the
world is wrong
on a basic level on a basic level okay
all right uh
so don't give me a book unless it agrees
with the gotcha
because i'm not interested okay all
right
and don't say it's just like what i
teach because it's not just like what
i'm teaching okay
like it really frustrates me
all right we're gonna do a little
sanskrit lesson
um
don't think this is useless okay when
you become a buddha you speak
sanskrit so come on learn a few words
now
it'll get your mind ready for later okay
okay so a picture say a picture
a picture
now this is an interesting word because
christina
when a sanskrit word starts with uh
it's
a negative but
here it's not
okay and it's very confusing okay so
it's not uh
it's up
yeah
yeah okay got it so yeah
so it's not a
picture like a video ignorance not
knowing right
it's not a pecha it's up
okay
so so don't get confused all right
what's that mean in tibetan it's tupa
what's tapa mean depend on the wall the
ladder depends on the wall the fire
depends on the wood and the wood depends
on the fire
dependent origination okay they both
depend on your seat okay it's not that
the fire is depending on the wood and
it's not that the woods depend on the
fire they are both depending on your
brain
and your theme okay got it
so dependence becomes crucial the word
affection becomes crucial now it's so
beautiful okay appa means away
and away comes from upper okay iksha
means you had paricha
to see nice
so you're looking to someone else for
help okay hey
uh christina i need some fingernail
clippers
you know and i i look away from myself
to you it's called looking away from
yourself to another person because you
you you need something you're depending
on i'm depending on
christina for that you know just a few
minutes ago
okay so that's called upper iksha
looking
looking over there uh for help looking
for what you need hey jingling can you
give me a pizza
i'm depending on you okay
affection i'm looking away to you
got it okay we had iksha
already when we did
parica yeah yeah and then uh
investigate
looking into something looking around
looking around digging around okay
uh yeah and don't forget by the way okay
tim you're only interested
the only one
this is the tibetan one is
ltos
okay
what's the root of that for fifty
dollars
wait you're looking here
he's too honored
uh tawa which means to look
so the root of the tibetan word is the
same as the root of the sanskrit okay
when you say dependent origination in
tibetan
you're saying look to somebody else
got it
the same route lt
okay
okay cool
all right that's your sanskrit lesson uh
i'm sorry that's a tough chapter that's
maybe the toughest
class we're gonna have
maybe
so don't get discouraged
uh look at it again and again and again
i you know
i spent i don't know
almost 30 years trying to figure this
stuff out
so don't get frustrated okay just keep
coming back to it and each time you come
back you'll understand a little more i
say
you know you can't really do mantras if
you if you don't understand this stuff
you you can i mean obviously anybody can
do mantras
but if you want them to be powerful
you have to understand this stuff okay
all right see you guys later